This is Dr. Solunius,
professor of anatomy, and
I'm going to give you a
lecture on the embryology
of the genitourinary system.
Okay, so we're going to
cover like five major topics,
the intermediate mesoderm
and the mesonephric kidney,
the glomerulus, and then
how the metanephric kidney
forms, and four is the
embryologic derivatives of
the cloaca and the urogenital
sinus, and then a little
bit on some pathologists,
you know, it's kind of
interesting stuff. Okay, so
let's get started with the
intermediate mesoderm. So
the intermediate mesoderm
is where you see the red.
It's between the paraxial
mesoderm and the lateral
plate mesoderm. Notice the
lateral plate mesoderm is
two layers, like a taco,
with a folding space.
The folding space
is the cilum where
the liver, the guts,
the intestines,
the stomach, all
of these things
are in the cilum.
And there is a
somatoplure on the upper
side and a splanchnoplure
on the lower side.
Now, notice how the
intermediate mesoderm is
connected to the cilum,
right? You see? To the
lateral plate mesoderm.
It's very well connected.
In the next picture, you're
going to see more of this.
Now, the intermediate
mesoderm differentiates
and makes glomeruli and tubing.
So, the kidney starts at
the very top, above the
heart, and it goes all the
way down to the bladder.
So it covers the
whole length of the
embryo, very much like
the vertebral column.
And it has glomeruli
in the whole area,
from the very top
to the very bottom.
That's called a
mesonephric kidney.
Here you can see how
the kidney forms in
relation to the paraxial
mesoderm and the lateral
plate mesoderm. Here,
the blue is the kidney
forming, and it is
connected to the cilum.
You see that?
The English spells cilum
in a different way.
There are three ways
of spelling cilum.
It means cavity. Cilum
means cavity. Okay.
So, the kidney forms
there, and then it's
connected to the
aorta. You can see that
in the second picture,
how the aorta has an
artery connecting to
the form and kidney.
And then above
this, a tube forms,
which is the excretory duct.
That's where the urine goes.
And also sperm and eggs, if
you're a fish, right? Okay.
So the kidney forms further.
You can see in the
third picture that the
kidney is more elaborate.
it, and you can see
the beginning of the
glomeruli. Those little
cups that form there
are the glomeruli.
Now, the kidney is
connected to the cilum. You
can see that, right? You
can see that in the third
picture. But eventually,
it separates from the
cilum, and it has its own
entity behind the cilum.
Here on the lower left you
can see a lot of glomeruli,
you know, all those little
things that look like
ranches, those are glomeruli,
and loops of henna and
all that, and the mesonaphric
duct is the duct that
takes the urine that is
produced, eggs and sperm too,
and excretes those things.
Now, in this picture here,
okay,
so let's see now. We have
three kinds of kidneys from
the intermediate mesotermic.
We have the pronephros,
which is a very primitive
ancient kidney. It
develops actually in
the neck, and we lose
it very early. I think
after four days, we
lose it. As a four-day
-old embryo disappears.
The mesonephros is very
strong and pervasive.
It's a strong kidney.
It starts at the top
and goes all the way to
the bottom of the body.
It's long and it has
ducts and tubules and
glomeruli, but the glomeruli
disappear in the adult
and the ducts remain.
So the plumbing of the
kidney, the tubes and the
ducts remain, but the
glomeruli disappear. Why
do they disappear? Here,
we need a kidney, well,
it's because a new kidney
is formed, the metanephrose.
And the metanephrose is
the new kidney, which
is the adult kidney with
new glomeruli in it.
Okay, now, we go back
to an embryo here. You
don't need to know all
these terms, right?
This is from a book I'm
writing, but you don't need
to know all these terms.
All you need to know is that
the intermediate mesoderm
is wedged between the
paraxial mesoderm and the
cilum, which is the lateral
plate mesoderm split in half.
So you have a splachnopleur
on one side and somatopleur
on the other side.
This is just to orient
you, to know where you are.
If you go to a grocery
store and look at
fish slices that they
sell, big fish, they
cut it in slices so
you can buy one or two
slices it looks just
like the slice here.
All the parts in there
are exactly like a fish
exactly
Okay, so now we go here
and see how the glomeruli
are formed from the
intermediate mesoderm.
You see these little
beads in B the central
one in B. Don't memorize
the dates Well, I
don't know the dates.
Don't memorize the dates.
Come on, okay? You know that.
So, in 25 days, you
form all these little
mesonephric structures,
which include glomeruli
and stuff. And it goes
from the top, from above
the heart, all the way
down to the bladder.
Now, what we're going
to do is talk about
some tubing here.
Now, in the adult,
this kidney was serving,
in the fish time,
it was serving,
we were fish about
300 million years
ago, we were fish.
Okay, so in the fish,
it's serving to excrete
the urine, excrete eggs
and sperm, right? Okay.
Now, what happened is the
kidney, the mesonafric
kidney said, I'm fed up with
this. I don't want to be
doing all this work. Why
don't I just do one thing?
So the body said, okay,
you know, you want to do
one thing? So I'm going to
remove you from the
responsibility of urine excretion
and also from egg
stuff, and all you have
to do is deal with the
male. So the plumbing
of the mesonephric
duct remained in the
adult, But the other
stuff disappeared.
Okay.
So here you can see what
happens to the
mesonephric duct.
It is red, and it is next
to the testes, if the
cornet is a testes, right?
I think it is in this case.
And the mesonephric
ducts will form
the epididymis and
the vas deferens.
Now, the paramezonephric
ducts, the blue ones, are not
part of the mesonephric
system Don't remember this,
at least Please, remember that
The blue, the paramezonephric
ducts, is a new structure
And it's formed from
the uterus So you see how
it converges at the bottom
and makes two little tubes
Those little tubes will form
the uterus So it's basically
a branching off from
the uterus And in the adult,
it will make the oviduct.
So the blue makes the
oviduct and the red
makes the vast difference
in the epididymis.
Now, on the bottom
here, you can see on the
left, the male, and on
the right, the female.
And you can see where
we have red in the
male, in the adult.
So there's a lot of
red in the male, in the
adult. The epididymis
is basically in the
vast difference.
In the female, on the
right side, we have
a lot of blue, which
is the uterus, the
upper part of the
******, and the oviducts.
But we still have some
red. You see those little
red dots next to the
oviducts? Those are
disintegrating parts of
the mesonophric system.
So both systems
exist in both sexes.
Now, this is a kidney, an adult
kidney. So that's a
metanephric kidney.
And you can see the
pyramids inside.
and you can see
the minor calyces
and the major calyces
in the ureter.
On the right side, you can
see a magnification of a
piece of a pyramid, not the
whole pyramid, just a little
tiny piece of it, maybe
one hundredth of a pyramid.
And then in there, you
can see the tubing. You
see the tubing? And then
all these little things
that look like peas or
flowers or whatever,
those are the glomeruli.
So the glomeruli are
arranged in sequences
around the plumbing,
which is the tubing.
Now, the tubing of the
kidney, like the collecting
tubules, the minor and major
calluses, the ureter, and all
this stuff, are derived
from the mesonephric system.
Metanephric system is
just the glomeruli, okay?
so this is a glomerulus so
we can start learning some
anatomy here so the glomerulus
is this artery so the
artery goes into this and it
comes out the other side so
there's no vein here no vein
it's all arterial it goes
into this bowman's capsule
which is this little cup
and inside this little cup
you have the artery twisting
around it goes like crazy
it goes this way and then
that way It turns around, it
goes this way. And then as
the blood surges around and
twists around, it excretes
urine on the outside. So
the urine is trapped on the
outside of this twisting
artery by centrifugal force.
So it's like you, when
you go to an amusement
park, when you go in a
rapid turn, you feel your
blood and your hair and
your head going in that
direction. So, that's how
you distill the urine out
of the blood. So, it's
a distillation machine.
And you have fluid accumulating
outside the artery,
and it's trapped around
by Bauman's capsule like
this. That's one
distillation, but there's two
distillations. The second
distillation is when the
urine enters the distal
convoluted tubule, and then
it goes around and around.
It goes all the way around.
I don't have a picture
of this now here. I mean,
I have pictures, but I
didn't put them in here,
okay, because this is
the embryology of the
kidney, not the
physiology of the kidney.
So then the convoluted tubule
twists around. it makes
the loop of henal maybe
you remember it from high
school and eventually it
goes up this way to the
proximal convoluted tubule
so by doing this more urine
is excreted and this is the
two distillation systems,
the glomerulus and the
convoluted tubule, right?
So that's how urine is produced
Now we have
the mesonephric part of
the kidney It starts from
an embryonic structure
called the ureteric bud.
What is the ureteric bud?
It's just a little branch.
Think of the mesonephric
tubing as a tree. So a
little branch of that tree
is called the ureteric bud.
But it has power. This little
thing has power because
it forms all the
metanephric things of the
kidney. The ureter, the
renal pelvis, we just said
that. The major and the minor
calluses, the collecting
ducts. and the collecting
tubules. All of those
are made by differentiation
of the ureteric ****,
okay? So that's
the collection, the
collecting portion
of the kidney.
Now, what's the excretory
part of the kidney?
The metanephric kidney
starts from a little lump
called the blastema. Blastema
means a growth, a growth.
Blastos in Greek is a
branch, a fresh branch
out of a vegetable,
okay? So, the excretory
portion of the kidney
starts with the metanephric
pastema, and that is
the Bowman's capsule,
the proximal convoluted
tubule, the loop of Henel,
the distal convoluted
tubule. So, all these
things are the excretory
portion of the kidney.
So, we have a collecting
portion of the excretions,
and then we have an
excretory portion, right?
So, first the excretory
portion makes its stuff, and
then the collecting portion
puts all the stuff in the
ureter, and then down the
bladder, and then you pee.
So, the metanephric
kidney is a conglomerate
of both mesonephric and
metanephric structures.
You understand this?
Mesonephric structures,
metanephric structures.
And so the metanephric
kidney is actually
containing a lot of
mesonephric stuff in it.
Okay?
So the book doesn't
make this very
clear, but I think I did. Okay?
Now, let's look at some of
these things in pictures.
So there's the ureteric
part. It's this little
branch. The ureteric part
is this little branch.
And then the metanephric
blastema that will make the
new glomeruli and all
this stuff is this brown
thing that connects to the
mesonephric curateric bud
branch. Okay, think of it
like a tree that branches.
That's the mesonephric
duct, the dark purple.
Okay,
so that's how the kidney
is formed. And it's down
here at the bottom of the
embryo next to the bladder.
Okay, the mesonephrous will
disappear except for the
plumbing. Okay, so we
need the plumbing, but the
actual glomeruli will
disintegrate. So all these little
tiny glomeruli of the
mesonephros will disintegrate.
The size of this embryo
is one-eighth of an inch.
That's how small it is, if
you can believe that. Yes,
of course, you know, we
start with a single cell, so
it's pretty big considering
the cell is like much bigger
than the cell, but it's
still one-eighth of an inch.
About 4 millimeters, actually,
if you want to go metric.
Okay, so now let's
see what we have done.
Let's summarize this. So
we have the mesonophric
duct in B and C and D,
this vertical shaft.
And then we have a
branch from it, okay?
Okay, the branch from it will
eventually become
the collecting tubal.
So there is the
collecting tubal at F. You
can see that. And then
the distal convoluted
tubal and the glomerulus
and stuff, the
loop of Henel and
stuff, is light brown.
So the connection
between the mesonephric
purple and the metanephric
part of the kidney,
you see it's a
conglomerate, right? We said
it's a conglomerate of
two different things.
It's somewhere between
the distal convoluted
tubal and the
collecting tubal, okay?
So memorize this for the exam.
Okay, now, I don't
believe this,
but I'm not a kidney scientist.
I'm just giving you the
lecture. I don't believe
this. I think scientists
are wrong. I don't
think there is such a
thing as a new glomerulus,
you know, like the
light brown on picture
F. I don't believe
that. Why would a body
make new glomeruli
when it has genes
for glomeruli from the
mesonephric system?
They must be the same genes.
So why do they say that
this thing is a new kidney,
the metanephric kidney?
Why do they say that? So I
thought and thought about
it. I actually stayed up
all night one night worrying
about this because I had to
give this lecture to you.
And I think my logical
explanation, it's a region.
It's a regional kidney.
It's the kidney at the
bottom of the system.
It's a new lump which
makes the kidney. And
that's what is metanephric,
not actually the
substance of it. The
substance of it, I suspect,
it's all mesonephric.
But it is in a new
position, so it's
like taking a chair
from your living room
and putting a chair
in your bedroom.
And then you say, well,
this is a new chair.
That's not a new chair.
It's the chair that you
took from the living
room and put it in the
bedroom. So this is
not a new kidney. It's
the original mesonefri
kidney, but it is a
new lump at the bottom.
And because the other
kidney disintegrates, the
scientists imagined
that it's something new.
Okay? That's my theory.
So I can't push that
theory down your throat
since basically it is
my theory. You know,
I'm just a teacher here.
So the fate of the
mesonephric kidney.
What happens to the
mesonephric kidney?
It's not lost
completely in the adult.
Just try to remember that.
Its tubing becomes
incorporated in
the reproductive
system of the males.
So the vast difference in the
epididymis is the
mesonephric duct.
also it makes the
trigon of the bladder
and the ureters and
all the plumbing of
the metanephric kidney
all the calluses
inside the whole thing
it's all mesonephric
in females the
parmesonephric duct is not
homologous to the mesonephric
duct no the parmesonephric
is a new structure
and it's derived from
the uterus as a
diverticulum of the uterus,
the parmesanephric duct
will form the oviduct.
So let's see here what we have.
Let me go back
and see this here,
there, okay.
So the oviduct on the
bottom right of the
female is the
parmesanephric diverticulum
the bladder, from the
uterus, I'm sorry.
So that's how the
system forms, right?
Now the red, all of
this redism is on aphric
duct and basically
does the epididymis
down here on the left,
the bottom left, and
then the vas deferens,
the duct deferens.
Okay, so let's go back to this.
Okay,
so in females the paramedic
So a nephric duct is
derived from the uterus as a
diverticulum. Now, let's see
here what we have. They
have mixed up the colors. So
I put on the bottom here,
the colors are backwards.
I'm tired of books,
you know, because
everybody does whatever
they want, okay?
So maybe they do it
on purpose. I don't
know. To torture the
medical students.
So the malarian duct is
the, in this case, it
should be blue. But
now it is red. Okay. So
the Millerian duct is
the paramezonephric duct.
So this is a male. So the
Millerian duct doesn't
interact with the testes,
right? But the mesonephric
duct, the purple, reacts
with the testes. And
the epididymis is these
little strands like this.
And the sperm will go by
meiosis. It will form in
the testes and it will go
down these tubules of the
epididymis and collect
itself into the mesonophric
duct, which will become
the vas deferens, okay?
You can see this
on the bottom. This
is a little bit
more differentiated.
And you can see how
the vas deferens
forms by the
mesonophric duct, okay?
What happens to the female
part? It disintegrates
but leaves a little
hint that it was there,
which is called the
appendix of the testes.
So when we're dissecting
the cadaver, I'll
show you the appendix
of the testes, okay?
It's a little dot
on the testes.
That used to be the
paramezonafric duct when both
sexes were in the embryo.
Now, when you have
two sexes in the embryo,
remember, we look at
the two sexes in the
embryo, we think that the
embryo has not decided
what it's going to be. No.
We don't know what the
embryo is going to be. And it
has both sexes, both
structures of both sexes in
it. The embryo cells know
very well what they're going
to be, but they are not
telling us. We're just
looking from far away with
a microscope and say, oh, it
looks like both sexes
are there. It's going to
decide someday if it's going
to be male or female. No.
The decision is made at the
moment of fertilization.
That's exactly when
the sex is determined.
So the cells of the
embryo know very
well what the future
is going to be like. We
don't know, but the
embryo knows, okay?
It's not talking to
us. That's the problem.
Okay, the female here.
So then this is all
the male stuff here,
right? So this is
going to disintegrate
in the female. So there
it is, bottom right.
bottom right. It's
all disintegrated.
And then the Millerian duct
or a Parmesan-Ephric duct,
the red, becomes the Oviduct
like I told you before.
The male stuff stays
on the membrane
here and it's
called a Pufferone.
Okay.
Parapufferone is like
people make up
names because they
have nothing else to do. Okay.
It's a Pufferone. It's
good enough. Okay.
Now we're going to
go to the cloaca.
The cloaca is a cup at
the bottom of the embryo,
at the very bottom, a
reproductive area, you
know, before the legs
start, okay? So it's a cup,
an upside-down cup,
like you can see in AA.
That's the cloaca. And the
word cloaca is from the
Romans used to have clay
tubes under the pavement
of the street to collect
the water when it rained.
Of course, it never rains
in a room, but anyway.
So they have these clay tubes
underneath to
collect the water,
and that's how the word
cloaca comes from, the
Latin for these clay
pots under the street.
Okay, so this is our
clay pot, our cloaca, and
it has three tubes in
it. It's got the ****
on the back, the ******
in the middle, the
purple, And then the yellow
is the bladder, okay?
So we've got the
bladder on one side,
we've got the ******
in the middle, purple,
and on the back,
green, is the ****.
So the cloaca has three
tubes in it. Now, if it's a
male, it's not going to have
this. It's not going to have
the ******, obviously.
It's going to just have the
bladder and the ****, okay?
So that's the cloaca. And
then what happens to the
cloaca? it forms a septum that's
called a urorectal septum
so it separates the ****
from the ****** and the bladder
it separates this septum
the urorectal septum
separates the cloaca into two
chambers the front chamber
is called a urogenital sinus
now this is a joke
because everybody talks
about a urogenital sinus
all the books you're
never going to find it
as genitourinary sinus
So why do they call the
system genitourinary?
I think it's only our
university that does this.
Everybody else knows the
system as urogenital. So it's
a urogenital system, not
the genitourinary system.
And I've told them a million
times, but then they either
hung up the phone on me
or complain or ignore my
email. So I've given up on
this. I don't know. Some dean,
not our dean now, some
dean, like three deans ago,
had the idea to call it
genitourinary, and it's stuck.
So we're stuck with
that name here.
Okay, it's the
urogenital system.
So these are the
derivatives of the cloaca.
Now, I made a drawing
of this right before the
lecture, so you can see here.
So, the cloaca has inside
an anorectal septum,
and the anorectal septum
separates the **** from the
other side. So, the front
part of the cloaca is
called the urogenital sinus.
Maybe we should call
it genitouritary sinus.
Anyway, the urogenital
sinus. Everybody
knows it that way in
France, in England, in
Germany. So, it's
called urogenital sinus.
Okay. Okay. And then inside
the urogenital sinus,
you have three openings.
You have the ******, the
bladder, and, of course,
the urethra of the *****
will form there. But I'm
not going to get into this
now because it's a little
bit too much for you.
The genital cervical
will make the erectile
tissues of the
******** and the *****.
But that's another
lecture, not this lecture.
Okay. So now let's
see the extra view of
the bladder. So, the
trigone of the bladder,
purple, is made out of
mesonephric material.
The yellow of the bladder is
made from the urogenital sinus.
So, the bladder is a composite
organ with a patch
on it, you know.
And the patch is
the trigone, which
means triangle in
Greek, okay? So,
anyway, so then we have,
in this trigon, we have the
mesonefric duct coming down
and fusing down there like
this, and then we have the
ureteric **** and the ureter
coming down like this. So,
the ureter and the ureteric
**** is there. I don't like
this drawing, but anyway,
that's what we have. I'm
tired of making my own
drawings, you know, so it's
not exactly accurate. I think.
Anyway, it's close enough.
You get the idea. So the
idea is the bladder is a composite
organ and the mesonephric
triangle of the bladder
is formed by extrophy.
What is extrophy? Extrophy
is when things flip over, so
the inside goes out. So if
you take a sweater and pull
it over your head out, then
the inside of the sweater
becomes outside and the
outside of the sweater, the
sleeves, go inside. So that's
an extrophy of your sweater,
okay? So the word extrophy
means turned inside out.
Okay, so now let's see. We
have now a summary here.
We talk about extrophy.
So we have the ureteric
part, which is part of
the mesonabric system,
and it makes the ureter,
the renal pelvis, major and
minor calluses, collecting
ducts, collecting tubules.
Then we have the metanephric
blastema, which is a
metanephric kidney, right?
And it makes bowel and
scapsule, proximal convoluted
tubal, the loop of hernal
distal convoluted tubal.
Then we have the mesonephric
duct. What's the mesonephric
duct? It makes the trigone
of the bladder, and it
gives rise to the ureteric
bud, that little branch
that will make the ureter.
That's why it's called
ureteric, because it will
make the ureter. and all
the calluses inside the
kidney. And then we have
the urogenital sinus,
which is part of the cloaca,
the front part of the
cloaca, and they'll make
the bladder, the urethra,
and the ******. So this
is your little summary.
Okay, now vascularization.
The kidney starts low
in the embryo. The first
embryo is like the real
early embryos, the first
week when you're one week
old, before the mother
knows that she's pregnant,
The embryo is going to
move its kidney, the
metanephric kidney, up. So
the kidney ascends, rises.
So it starts at the bottom
of the bladder and goes
up. What is interesting is
that it gets vascularized
by the arteries of the
body, mostly the aorta,
as you can see here. But
it changes its arterial
vascularization depending
where it is. So when it
was down here, it was
probably the internal iliac.
When it was here, it was
the external iliac, the
common iliac. And then
it goes up, and then it
vascularizes itself on the
way up like this. And as it
arises, as the kidney rises,
the ureter gets longer.
Okay. And then it stops
when it meets the adrenal
gland. The suprarenal gland
does not rise with the
kidney. It's always where
it is. So when the kidney
hits the adrenal gland,
it says, I guess I rose
enough. Now we can do an
experiment. Take the adrenal
gland out and see if the
kidney will keep rising
until it goes into your
mouth and the eyeballs.
But I don't know who's going to
do this experiment.
It's not me.
Okay.
So somehow the
adrenal gland says,
you reached your destination.
Okay.
Now, why is the system
called urogenital?
genitourinary at our
university don't forget this
why the system is called
urogenital where do
the two systems meet euro
means urine urine right
genital means sexual
parts right so how is it
called urogenital where
is the connection okay the
connection is inside
the prostate in the male
so the bladder is above
the prostate on the left
here you can see the
bladder above the prostate
And then the prostate is right
under the bladder. It's purple.
And inside the prostate,
there is this little,
it looks like a little
tube with a little
opening, the orifice of
the prostatic utricle.
So the orifice of
the prostatic utricle
is exactly where the
genital part connects.
So the ***** comes out
of there, you know,
into the prostate.
So basically, the urine
passes on either side of
this tube. So the urine is
here, and the reproductive
***** goes and mixes with
the urine or whatever
right here. And that's
why it's called urogenital
system. It's the connection
of the two systems.
How about the female?
Where is it in the female?
Well, in the female, it
is in the urethra. The
urethra is totally
separate, the bladder and
the urethra. In the
female, it's totally uro
system, right? And it
becomes genital because the
urethra empties inside
the front of the ******.
So where the ******
terminates, there's a little
lump at the dorsal side.
I can show you in the lab,
and that's where the urethra
is. So the urethra is
there. So it's, again,
urogenital, uro and genital.
Okay,
common pathologists. Let's
do some pathologists.
Okay, the imperforated
****. You might get
in the board exams a
question from this.
Imperforated **** is the
**** is not open, and
that's because of the
urorectal septum, which
is dysfunctioning. So
the urectal septum will
form the sphincters and
the opening of the ****
into the cloaca, right?
So if that doesn't work,
then you end up with a
baby that cannot ****.
So after one day, the
mother realizes and the
father that there's something
wrong with the baby.
But hopefully the doctors
will have seen that at
the birth room in the
hospital. So when When they
check the babies, they
check if the testes have
descended, they check
the color, the breathing,
the nostrils, and
they check the ****.
So then they have to see
that the **** is open, okay?
Now this is part of a
system called the Vacterial
Association, and many times
all these abnormalities
occur at the same time
because all of them are in
different chromosomes and
different genes. Somehow
the genes talk to each
other. So all these things
go wrong at the same time.
So what is bacterial?
It's vertebral anomalies.
V is vertebral anomalies.
**** atresia. That means
the **** is not open,
right? Atresia means not
open. So that's the A.
And then we have cardiovascular
abnormalities. That
will be like the foramen
ovale or the ductus
arteriosus. something is
wrong with the heart, right?
So that's the C,
cardiovascular abnormalities.
And then we have the T.
The T is tracheophageal
fistula, which means
there's a branch from the
trachea that leads nowhere.
So the air goes inside
this chamber and it doesn't
go into the lungs well,
you know. So that's the
tracheophageal fistula.
And that's the T.
And then esophageal
atrecia is when the
esophagus doesn't form.
That's pretty bad, okay?
I don't know if they
live, but anyway.
So esophageal atrecia is the E.
And then renal anomalies, and
we're talking about them, okay?
So the renal anomalies,
I'll show you some pictures,
are the R. And the final
one is limb defects. So
usually you have missing
limbs or missing hands
or the feet are bent
inward or something like
this. So those are the
limb defects. And this is
called the bacterial
association. A lot of these
things happen together.
If you get all these
things together, then
it's a disaster, I think.
I don't know if they
live. I don't know.
Okay.
So another one is
hydronephrosis. And
hydronephrosis is when the
glomeruli don't work well.
So, the fluid accumulates
into the ureter
and bulges the uterus,
the ureter out with
the fluid and the uterus,
the ureter expands.
And this is
hydronephrosis. That
means the glomeruli
don't work well.
This one is renal agenesis.
Agenesis means not developed.
A, the A means no in Greek.
So renal agenesis means
a kidney is not formed.
Well, this is not so bad,
actually. One kidney is
enough. But sometimes because
it's one and it's a baby,
it expands and enlarges. So
it's a hypertrophic kidney.
It's huge because it does
the job of two kidneys.
But in an adult, if one
of the kidneys dies,
the body doesn't know very
much of it. It doesn't
have very many effects
because the kidney
is just there for
symmetry. You know, all the
organs are doubled
because of the symmetry of
the body. So you have
two transverse processes,
two iliac crests, two ribs,
one on the other side,
two thyroids
and everything is
double two lungs
not everything is
double I don't want
to get into this but
anyway the symmetry
of the body is why
we have two kidneys
so you can donate a
kidney if somebody
needs a kidney you'll
do just fine with one
oligohydramnios
oligohydramnios means a
little bit of amniotic fluid,
not a lot. So the amniotic
fluid is the pee of the
baby. So the baby pees,
and then that's the fluid.
And it is the fluid that
the baby swallows, and it
circulates it. So they drink
their own pee, and that
pee is re-peed with more pee
as the embryo grows bigger
and bigger, and the feces
grows bigger and bigger.
So when you have not a lot
of amniotic fluid, the fetus
and the baby or whatever,
the embryo and the fetus,
stick to the wall of the
uterus, and then they get
deformed. So their feet get
deformed, their arms get
deformed, their face sometimes
sticks and gets deformed.
And that's forever, like
you're born this way. So this
is called olivohydramnios,
and it is the lack of fluid
that protects the fetus
and helps the fetus develop
normally. The opposite of
this is polyhydramnios, which
is the opposite. There's a
lot of fluid. Why is there
a lot of fluid? It's because
the embryo and the fetus
don't swallow it. They don't
swallow enough of it. and
then the swallowing of the
fluid is necessary to develop
a normal tongue to develop
a normal teeth to develop
all this part so it's
necessary for swallowing to
happen to form the genetics
of the structures correctly
the same with the arms
and the legs they have
to be moving Otherwise,
the joints don't form
correctly. So everything
has to be functioning
in order to, which is
interesting. So the
function helps the
creature form normally.
So the same with the heart.
It beats before it is a
heart. So the blood beats and
the cells beat even before
it is a heart. So the
function is a part of the
development, the correct
development of the structures.
The function is part of it.
So when we have excess
accumulation of fluid, people
will know that because
when the wet water breaks,
you have like a gallon
or two gallons of fluid
coming out. That's a bad
sign. It's just a lot of
fluid, and maybe the
doctors will say, you know,
maybe we'll have a case
of polyhydramnios, okay?
And then the baby
hopefully will start
swallowing correctly,
and this causes diabetes,
maternal diabetes. It can
cause this thing, too.
Okay, the horse kidney,
that's famous. I
don't know why it's
famous. Everybody around
the world loves the
horseshoe kidney.
Horseshoe kidney
is where the two
kidneys are connected
by mistake, okay?
But it doesn't hurt
the kidneys. It's
asymptomatic. You can have
a horse kidney, live a
normal life. You can
be an Olympic athlete.
You can do anything you want.
But what happens is when
the kidney rises, it can't
rise very much because
the inferior mesenteric
artery stops it. So it stops
at the inferior mesenteric
artery. You can see that
in the drawings, right?
So it gets stuck low.
That's okay. It's still
functioning, and it's
just like one of those
things. We once had a
horseshoe kidney here in
the lab. I remember all the
students loved to see
that thing, and they
accumulated it at that table,
and eventually somebody
broke it with their
finger. Okay, so much for
that. I was going to save
it, but then it broke.
Okay.
Now, pelvic kidney.
What's a pelvic kidney?
You remember we said
the kidney rises?
Okay.
So, a kidney that
doesn't rise is called a
pelvic kidney. So, it's
low next to the bladder.
There's no problem
with this. It functions
normally. You wouldn't
know you have it.
How would you know unless you
had an x-ray or
something? Okay.
So, that doesn't hurt anything,
but it is called
a pelvic kidney.
Okay.
So, we're done. So let's
summarize some stuff
here. Okay, so the
ureteric bud is part of
the mesonephric duct.
Okay, it's a branch.
Now, this ureteric bud
will form the ureter, the
renal pelvis, the major
and minor calluses, the
collecting ducts, and
the collecting tubules.
Okay, now the metanephric
kidney. The metanephric
blastema, it's that
little lump of brown that
sticks next to the ureteric
bud. It sticks to the
ureteric bug, and they
talk to each other and say,
Hey, I'm the ureteric bug.
I'm going to invade you
and make all kinds of
calluses and collecting
ducts and collecting tubules
inside. Is that okay?
And then every plastema
says, Sure, go ahead and
invade me. Okay. So then he
makes the Bowman's capsule,
the proximal convoluted
tubules, the loop of Henel,
the distal convoluted
tubules, and stuff.
I misspell Henel.
It should be with a
capital H because it's
the name of a guy.
Okay.
So the mesonephric duct
forms the trigone of the
bladder, extra fear, remember
that, for the board exams,
ureteric bud, and also the vast
deferens in the
epididymis in the male.
The urogenital sinus is the
front part of the cloaca,
the anterior part
of the cloaca,
and it connects to the
urethral bladder and the ******
so there's your little
summary I think we did it all
ok